# Antônio Ferreira

+55 (81) 98695-3988 antoniolfnt@outlook.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/antoniolfnt/ www.github.com/antoniolfnt

Data Governance | Data Engineer

Information Technology Manager, certified in Scrum (SFPC) and Kanban (KEPC), dedicated to developing and learning about solutions for collecting, analyzing large data sets, creating and maintaining data pipelines and data structures. Currently, I am specializing in supporting all initiatives in delivering the data strategy, specifically activities related to Data Governance, Data Quality, Data Profiling, Agile Change Delivery, with some elements of Data Architecture, Business Intelligence and Data Science.

## **Main Skills**

- Data Engineering
- Scrum/Kanban
- Data Governance
- Project Management
- Data Quality
- Big Data

# Work experience

Weduu (Full-time)

12/2022-Present

### Data Governance / Data Engineer

# Job description:

- Participate in and support the full project life cycle (initiation, planning, requirements, analysis, design, development, quality assurance, user-acceptance testing, deployment, and production support);
- Implement and maintain data policies and processes and provide ongoing monitoring and reporting on those processes;
- Designing, building and launching, reliable and scalable data quality architecture solutions for product evolution focusing on Data Analytics, Machine Learning and AI;
- Creation of data repositories for storage and integration of large volumes such as: Data Lakes, Data Ware Houses, Structured and Unstructured data.
- CRD Data (Part-time)

09/2022-Present

# Data Project Manager (independent consultant)

Job Description:

- Troubleshoot and resolve product issues and concerns;
- Assisting customers face-to-face with any billing and/or equipment issues;
- Provide information about the data products and services;
- Seek and organize the implementation of the detected problem solutions.

#### Kev proiects / Task

- Instructor for the course "Beginner Data Analyst" for developers at the company;
- Management of developer allocation for projects;
- Creation of software requirements documentation;
- Conduct of meetings with investors.
- MV Sistemas

09/2021-09/2022

#### Data Engineer | Business Intelligence Analyst Junior

Job Description:

- Build, update and maintenance for ETL solutions on-premises using Pentaho, SQL, Python;
- Answering calls from customers for corrections of BI applications;
- Implementation of Business Intelligence architecture for new costumers;
- Development and maintenance of dashboards in: Qlik Sense and Tableau;
- Responsible for the definition, development and maintenance of the Data Quality Management methodology, principles and processes, as well as their documentation in terms of policies.

## Key Projects / Tasks

- Creation of a new data product on-premises using Apache Airflow for the pipeline, pandas for data transformation at the finish of the processes, the data is post by an API;
- Active participation in meetings and discussions to promote a new architecture ETL for new customers;
- Planning the new ETL architecture on cloud using: Airflow, Spark, Docker, Python, Postgres and Oracle;
- Update of an old project using: Pentaho, SQL, and Postgres;
- Active in lectures to promote data quality and data governance all over the company.

 Cidadão Fiscal Data Analyst (Intern) 05/2020 - 09/2020

#### Job Description:

- Use of data analysis and artificial intelligence to monitor the spending of Pernambuco politicians;
- Improved format for displaying deputies' expenses for the population;
- Data extraction in the Transparency Portal and in the ALEPE portal, modeling, cleaning and transformation to assemble the Dashboards. (Power BI, Excel, Python).

#### Key projects / Tasks:

- Implementation and redesign of new website;
- Creation of a new data visualization template (Power BI) based on the new look of the ONG;
- More than 2T Data Management.

## **Education**

- Faculdade Metropolitana Postgraduate degree (MBA) Data Science and Big Data Analytics – 2023-2023
- University of Chicago Professional Education Artificial Intelligence and Data Science for Leaders – 2022–2022
- UNIFG Associate Degree Information Technology Management 2019-2021

#### **Further Education & Certificates**

- Project Management Fundamentals Google, 2022
- Data Pipelines com Azure Stack Technology, 2022
- Certification Scrum Foundation Professional Certificate (SFPC)
- Certification Kanban Essentials Professional Certificate (KEPC)
- Data Mining EAD Laureate, 2020
- Nano Course Business Intelligence (BI) FIAP, 2021
- Introduction to Big Data, FIA Business School, 2019

### **General Skills**

Language Skills: Portuguese – Native | English – (B2).

**Other skills:** Apache Airflow, Business Intelligence, Big data, Agile, Cobit 2019, DAMA DMBOOK, Scrum, Kanban, Data Analytics, Microsoft Power BI, Tableau, Qlik Sense, Data Engineering, Data Science, Data Governance, Data Quality, Docker, Big Data, Data Management, Data Pipelines, Apache Spark, Azure, Amazon, Google Cloud Platform (GCP)